<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Discourse upon usury, or, Lending money for increase (occasioned by Mr. David Jones's late farewel sermon) proving by undeniable arguments the lawfulness thereof and answering the plausible objections from Scripture, councils, and fathers against it / published at the request of several judicious and sober Christians for the information and satisfaction of all such as have or may be concerned in the matter of so general and weighty importance.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36116</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1629</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14405</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11844785</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11844785</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49813</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36116)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49813)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 26:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Discourse upon usury, or, Lending money for increase (occasioned by Mr. David Jones's late farewel sermon) proving by undeniable arguments the lawfulness thereof and answering the plausible objections from Scripture, councils, and fathers against it / published at the request of several judicious and sober Christians for the information and satisfaction of all such as have or may be concerned in the matter of so general and weighty importance.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Crouch ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Columbia University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jones, David, 1663-1724? --  Farewel sermon preached to the united parishes of St. Mary Woolnoth, and St. Mary Wool-Church-Haw.</term>
               <term>Usury --  Biblical teaching.</term>
               <term>Interest --  Biblical teaching.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49813:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49813:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE UPON USURY: OR, Lending MONEY for INCREASE. (Occaſſioned by Mr. <hi>David Jones's</hi> late Farewel SERMON) PROVING By undeniable Arguments the Lawfulneſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and Anſwering the Plauſible Objections from Scripture, Councils, and Fathers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſſt it.</p>
            <p>PUBLISHED At the Requeſt of ſever<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l Judicious and Sober Chriſtians, for the Information and Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>action of all ſuch as have or may be concerned in this Matter of ſo General and Weighty Importance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Crouch</hi> at the Corner of <hi>Pope's-Head-Alley</hi> over-againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:49813:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49813:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>MR. Jones</hi>'s Farewel Sermon has been the occaſſion of much Diſſcourſe in City and Country, eſpecially that part relating to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury, a Subject which of late years has not been (as I know) much controverted on one ſide or ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but now being ſo zealouſly oppoſed by Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> (who is deſervedly reſpected for his Courage and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity in preaching down the Vices of the Times) it has occaſioned a more than ordinary Concernment of Spirit in many (I hope I may ſay good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, who have a hearty reſpect for Mr. <hi>Jones,</hi> and have been or are concern'd in the buſineſs of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury) to examine this matter a little more cloſely than they have hitherto done, and the dealings of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury are become univerſal, reaching Nobility and Gentry as well as Merchants and Tradeſmen, ſo that all have need to be ſatisfied, whether it be lawful or not? The Writer hereof owns that upon reading that Sermon, and the hard things that are there ſpoken againſt all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury by Councils and Fathers, he began to doubt whether <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury were now lawful to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: This put him upon the ſerious ſearch of
<pb facs="tcp:49813:3"/>the Point, as well from Scripture, as from thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of note in our Country that have wrote againſt it, and ſome others that have written for it. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the whole, he declares he is fully ſatisfied of the Lawfulneſs of it; and that it may be managed with as much Juſtice and Charity as Buying and Selling, Letting or Setting of Houſes or Land, which are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to as great Abuſes as Lending for Intereſt. The Reaſons of his Satisfaction are ſet down in this Writing, to which he could have added many more, had it been needful: He has communicated theſe to ſeveral Miniſters, and other underſtanding and ſerious Chriſtians, who do acknowledge their full Satisfaction in the Arguments and Reaſons here produc'd, and have requeſted the Writer to publiſh them to the World, that Satisfaction may he given to others, eſpecially ſuch who may have received Impreſſions to their Damage from that part of Mr. <hi>Jones</hi>'s Sermon which relates to this matter. The Writer has ſtudied Verity and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, and as much plainneſs as he could, to render his Arguments Convincing and Evident even to an ordinary Capacity, having (he hopes) ſatisfactorily and clearly anſwered all thoſe Pleas againſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury from Scripture, Councils and Fathers, or from the Nature of the thing it ſelf which hath been urged by Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> or others.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49813:3"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE UPON USURY: OR, Lending Money for Increaſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Jews by God's own appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were obliged to ſeveral ſorts of Laws, as firſt Ceremonial or Typical, ſuch as Circumciſion, the Paſſover, Sacrifices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They that are againſt all Uſury will own that Chriſtians are not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to theſe. Secondly, To Laws which in their very Nature are Moral and Perpetual, and therefore bind us as much as them. And that the Law againſt Uſury is not of this ſort, I
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49813:4"/>think is plain, becauſe God did permit even the Jews to lend upon Uſury to Strangers, which he would not have done, had it been a Sin in its own Nature, and as obligatory to all as the other Moral Laws are: For God did not give them leave to Rob, or to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Adultery, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Drunk with Strangers, provided they did not do ſo among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: Nay, God commanded the Jews that they ſhould not oppreſs even Strangers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they themſelves were Strangers in the Land of <hi>Egypt.</hi> From whence it is plain, That Uſury in its own Nature is not unlawful or unjuſt, nor can be reckoned Oppreſſion, as they that plead againſt it affirm it is. For had it been ſo, then God would not have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the Jews to lend to Strangers upon U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury as he did; Nay, God made it one of the Bleſſings that ſhould attend their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that <hi>They ſhould lend to many N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tions, and not borrow;</hi> (this could never be meant of Free Loan.) So that for ought I can ſee, an Ability to lend upon Uſury to many, was one of the Bleſſings of <hi>Canaan.</hi> Thirdly, God obliged the Jews to certain Politick Laws, which were, <hi>Firſt,</hi> Either ſuch as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected Common Juſtice (of which there are
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49813:4"/>abundance of Inſtances) or <hi>Secondly,</hi> Laws of Charity and Kindneſs one to another, and that not only in general, but in particular Inſtances (among which that of lending free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was one) and which otherwiſe they had not been bound perpetually to obſerve from the nature of the things themſelves; and which Precepts (reſpecting both Juſtice and Charity) were part of that Theocracy or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Government that was peculiar to them as Jews, I ſhall here ſet down ſome of theſe Laws of Charity.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Exod. XXII. 25, 26.</bibl> 
               <hi>If thou lend Money to any of my People that is poor by thee, thou ſhalt not be to him as an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurer, neither ſhalt thou lay upon him <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury. If thou takeſt at all thy Neighbours Rayment to Pledge, thou ſhalt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver it to him by that the Sun goeth down.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Levit. XXV. 35, 36, 37.</bibl> 
               <hi>And if thy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be waxen poor, and fallen in decay with thee, then thou ſhalt relieve him, yea though he be a Stranger or a Sojourner, that he may live with thee, take thou no <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury of him or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe: Thou ſhalt not give him thy Money for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury, nor lend him thy Victuals for Increaſe.</hi>
            </q>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:49813:5"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>Deut. XXIII. 19, 20.</bibl> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not lend upon <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury to thy Brother; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury of Money, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury of Victuals, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury of any thing that is lent upon <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto a Stranger thou mayeſt lend upon <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Deut. XXIV. 19, 20, 21.</bibl> 
               <hi>When thou cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt down thy Harveſt in the Field, and haſt forgot a Sheaf in the Field, thou ſhalt not go again to fetch it; It ſhall be for the Stranger, for the Fatherleſs, and for the Widow. When thou beateſt thine Olive Tree, thou ſhalt not go over the Boughs again, it ſhall be for the Stranger,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>When thou gathereſt the Grapes of thy Vineyard, thou ſhalt not glean it after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, it ſhall be for the Stranger,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Deut. XV. 1, 2, 3.</bibl> 
               <hi>At the end of every Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Years thou ſhalt make a Releaſe, and this is the manner of the Releaſe; Every Creditor that lendeth ought unto his Neighbour ſhall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe it, he ſhall not exact it of his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, or of his Brother. Of a Forreigner thou mayeſt exact it.</hi>
            </q>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:49813:5"/>
            <p>Now I humbly conceive it may be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably queſtioned, Whether theſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures do totally forbid lending upon Uſury, even to all ſorts of Jews. You ſee there is two places in <hi>Exodus</hi> and <hi>Levitious</hi> that plainly limit it to poor Neighbour-Jews. Now all the Fundamental Laws which God gave the People of the Jews, as a Nation, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Moral, Ceremonial, or Judicial, are ſet down in the Four Books of <hi>Exodus, Leviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, Numbers,</hi> and <hi>Deuteronomy;</hi> only here is the difference between <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> and the other Three Books, that <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> doth moſtly contain a Repetition of Laws already eſtabliſhed in the other Three Books, or in ſome of them. And though theſe Laws, or any of them, be afterwards mentioned in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the reſt of the Books of the Of Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, yet it is but in a way of Repetition or Inforcement of the Old Laws already gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven forth, without any Alteration or Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as to the Subſtance of them: And therefore when in the other Books mention is made of any of thoſe Laws in general, (as ſome times there is) and any Diſpute ſhould ariſe about the meaning of theſe Laws, muſt we not have recouſe to the Original Sanction
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49813:6"/>or Eſtabliſhment, ſet down in ſome of the ſaid Four Books. Thus ought we to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in the Caſe of Uſury in thoſe Books where the Law about Uſury is eſtabliſhed, namely in <hi>Exodus</hi> and <hi>Levitious;</hi> there is no Obligation to lend freely to any but the Poor: And though in <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> the Law of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury is repeated in general, without mention of Poor or Rich, and the like we have in ſome other Books of the Old Teſtament, yet I think it is very plain, that all theſe Places (as well in <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> as in the other Books) muſt have a Reference to, and be expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by thoſe two expreſs Original Laws eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed concerning Uſury in <hi>Exodus</hi> and <hi>Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus,</hi> and not the contrary, as ſome would have it; and theſe Laws twice mention poor Jews, and once poor Strangers, and give no Rule for Lending or not Lending the Rich of one ſort or of another: Therefore ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> there is no new Law ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded about Uſury, but only the former Law in general repeated; and ſince neither here, nor in other places of the Old Teſtament, there is any Law forbidding to lend to rich Jews, Why may we not (without putting any force upon thoſe places) ſay we muſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49813:6"/>underſtanding by them ſuch Uſury as in the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal Law was forbidden (that is to ſay) the taking it of poor Jews and poor Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. And if they might take Increaſe of none that were Jews, though never ſo Rich, why ſhould the Holy Ghoſt twice mention theſe Expreſſions, <hi>If thy Brother be poor, thou ſhalt lend without <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi> Surely he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have repeated theſe If's twice over, if Rich as well as Poor were concerned in the Prohibition; but in all the places where U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury is forbidden, he would have forbid it abſolutely without any Limitation: And for the ſame Reaſons we muſt not ſo conſtrue any places in the Prophets, as to take away any Liberty or Priviledge given (either ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, or by a plain, natural, and neceſſary Conſequence) in the Original Fundamental Laws: this would be to pervert (not inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret) Scripture, and would make the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets Law-givers, not Law Interpreters. But not to inſiſt upon this any further; ſuppoſe the Caſe had been that no Uſury was to be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of any Jews, Poor of Rich, which is the Opinion of thoſe that oppoſe all Uſury or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe for Lending of Money.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:49813:7"/>
            <p>Now here is the great Queſtion I would be reſolved in by thoſe that would have all kinds of Uſury, or Increaſe for lending Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, unlawful to Chriſtians, Whether if Chriſtians are obliged to this Jewiſh Law a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Uſury (which is a Law of Charity) they are not as well obliged to all the other Laws or Inſtances of Charity I have named before, and the reſt, enjoyned to the Jews in the Old Law?</p>
            <p>That Chriſtians are obliged to Charity in general, by many Precepts in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is not to be queſtioned; but whether they are obliged to ſhew it always in thoſe particular Inſtances that the Jews were, I not only queſtion, but poſitively deny. Nor do I believe the Oppoſers of all Uſury do think themſelves obliged to thoſe other Inſtances I have named, which are as great, or rather greater Acts of Charity than lending Money freely. And I would fain know why they are ſo ſtrict for this one Inſtance, and yet at the ſame time can paſs over the others, although both are equally Commanded by God in the Old Teſtament. I do not think it unlawful for a Chriſtian to ſhew his Charity in any of the afore-mentioned Inſtances of Charity, any
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49813:7"/>more than in this of lending freely: Nay, I wiſh Chriſtians were more plentiful in ſuch Acts of Kindneſs as lending freely, forgiving poor Debtors once in Seven years, in leaving at Harveſt time ſome of the Fruits of the Earth for the Poor, and the like: But the Queſtion in Debate is, Whether Chriſtians are obliged upon account of theſe Jewiſh Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, under the Penalty of Sin, always to ſhew their Charity in theſe particular Inſtances; Hath not a Chriſtian in Harveſt time the choice either to cauſe all his Fruits to be brought home, and leave hone for the Poor, and in lieu thereof ſhew his Charity in another way or manner? Whether if a Chriſtian forget a Sheaf in his Field in Harveſt time, he may not ſend for it without ſinning? Whether ſuch as take Garments in Pledge for Money lent, may not forbear to reſtore them again by that the Sun goeth down? I think none will deny this Liberty to Chriſtians; but the very Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Law denied it to the Jews; for though they might be Charitable in other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, as well as theſe, yet theſe muſt not be omitted, being expreſly Commanded. Now if a Chriſtian is not bound to ſuch particular Inſtances of Charity, but is left free as to the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49813:8"/>Kinds and Methods of Charity; and if lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Money freely be an Act of Charity or Kindneſs (as certainly it is) why is a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an perpetually obliged to this Inſtance, any more than to the former Inſtances of Charity? If they that oppoſe all Uſury ſay, Though the other Inſtances of Charity are Commanded of God, yet they peculiarly belonged to the Jews, and were ſome of their Judicial or Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical Laws that are not obligatory to Chriſtians now, but the Law againſt Uſury is; Then let them ſhew me their Warrant for making this Difference and Diſtinction between one and another. It is plain all the other Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Charity I have named are practicable in their own Nature in a Chriſtian Country, as much as the Law againſt Uſury; nor are they any where prohibited in the Goſpel. A Man may be a very good Chriſtian, and yet at the end of every Seven years releaſe all that ſhall then owe l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m any Money if he pleaſe. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, I deſire thoſe that are againſt all Uſury, or Increaſe for lending Money, as wicked and ſinful, ſeriouſly to conſider that the very ſame Jewiſh Law that forbids to lend for Uſury, commands to lend without it to thoſe that are waxen poor. Now by this, they that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49813:8"/>gainſt all Uſury, are obliged to be as careful to lend their poor Neighbours when they want, as they are conſcientious not to do it upon U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury; or otherwiſe they perform but the leaſt part of that Law; for lending Money freely in ſuch a caſe, is a greater kindneſs than the meer ſcrupling to take Uſe: Therefore it will do well for ſuch to take care, while they ſhew their Zeal in ſhunning all Uſury, they do not fall into the greater Sin of Hypocriſie in being ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable as not to lend at all when the Caſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires it; for it's a greater deed of Charity to lend upon moderate Uſury, even to the Poor, than not to lend to them at all in their Wants. Now if the Law to lend Money freely were a particular Law of Charity, and not of Common Juſtice, and peculiarly relating to the Jews as ſuch, and not univerſally obliging them nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, (for they might lend to all the World at Uſury, except to one another, and to poor Strangers that were with them, and the Jews were but a handful in compariſon of the reſt of the World) If the Gentile Chriſtians are no more perpetually obliged to this Inſtance of Charity than the others before-mentioned; (as I am fully ſatisfied they are not.) If to lend upon moderate Increaſe be not in its own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49813:9"/>unjuſt (as I hope I have in part already proved, and ſhall preſently further manifeſt by anſwering the moſt material Objections againſt it) If it be not forbidden in the Goſpel (as I am ſatisfied it is not) then I humbly conceive that thoſe Arguments againſt all Uſury, or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe upon Loan of Money, taken not only from the Old Teſtament, but from Councils, Fathers, and other Doctors and Writers in former Ages (that are ſo cried up as Enemies of all Uſury) will fall to the Ground; unleſs Chriſtians muſt be compelled ſo far to Judaize as perpetually to obſerve thoſe other Laws of Charity impoſed upon the Jews, which I doubt they will not, nor indeed are they obliged to do ſo; though they who oppoſe all Uſury as unlawful, are bound ſo to do from their own Principles or Arguments, or muſt confeſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves guilty of unaccountable partiality in their zealous aſſerting of, and ſtickling for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuity of one Jewiſh Law of Charity or Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and diſobeying and rejecting all the reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But it is objected, 'Tis ſtrange ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Fathers, Councils, and other holy Men in all Ages have ſo condemned Uſury, if it were not unlawful; and who ſhall be believed, they, or thoſe that would have it lawful?</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:49813:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, neither the one nor the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without due proof: If this be a good Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument againſt all Increaſe for Loan of Money, it would be ſo againſt the Proteſtant Religion it ſelf; and that Queſtion of the Papiſts (I think) would be unanſwerable, <hi>Where was your Religion before</hi> Luther? The Queſtion is nor whether is beſt, to lend Money freely, or upon Increaſe; for I grant it moſt Chriſtian for them that are able to lend Money freely when the reaſon of the Caſe requires it: So if poor People come to buy of a rich Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man neceſſary Proviſion or Apparel, it is better and more pleaſing to God, to give away his Profit to ſuch than to take it; yea, and it may be a Sin in ſome Caſes of Extream Neceſſity to exact of the Poor what is due from them: But is buying and ſelling for profit, in a way of Common Juſtice therefore unlawful in its own Nature. It may be a Sin (in ſome Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances a Borrower may be in) not only to force him to pay Uſury, but the very Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal, or at leaſt the whole of it: But muſt this be therefore obſerved of all as a general Rule, and in all Caſes and Circumſtances.</p>
            <p>And as to the Objection that ſo many Holy Men and Councils are againſt all Uſury,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49813:10"/>I anſwer, I doubt not I ſhall preſently make it out, that all theſe Councils and Fathers were not againſt all Uſury or Increaſe in the Senſe of thoſe that now plead againſt it: But put the Caſe they, or ſome of them were, I ſay we are not to pin our Faith upon ſuch, no more in this than in any other Caſes or Inſtances, wherein many (if not moſt) of theſe Fathers and Councils have erred, and that in many A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Church. It is well known that the indiſcreet Zeal of many Holy Men and Councils has been the Original, as well as a Means of the Continuance of Abundance of Superſtition and Idolatry that has been practiſed in many Ages of the Church, ſuch as the Maſs, Praying to or for the Dead, and many Errours about the Sacraments, beſides ſeveral other Doctrinal Errours from the Primitive Age of the Church down to this time, which are all now diſcard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and diſowned by Proteſtants: And why are we bound to think them any more infallible in their Judgments about Uſury, wherein they might more eaſily miſtake it (being expreſly forbidden to the Jews in the Old Teſtament in ſome Caſes;) I will not pretend to have my ſelf read either the Councils or Fathers, but I have read thoſe who have given ſome
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49813:10"/>account of them relating to the Matters in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate; I doubt not thoſe Councils and Fathers (whole Opinions and Judgments we have moſt reaſon to value, though none to build on) are ignorantly or careleſly miſrepreſented by thoſe that are againſt all Increaſe upon Loan of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</p>
            <p>The firſt <hi>Nicene</hi> Council is ſuppos'd to be the beſt, as well as the firſt General Council, after that of the Apoſtles, and they did indeed forbid all Uſury; but to whom? to all the Clergy, not to the Laity; the Words of the Council, in effect amount to no more than this, <hi>Whoever of the Clergy, for filthy Lucres ſake exerciſeth <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury, let him be Depoſed.</hi> And this by the way ſeems to imply, That Uſury in its own Nature was not unlawful, (for then it ſhould have been Cenſured in the Lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty alſo) but they thought it did not look well in the Clergy to receive Uſury. Now it the firſt and beſt General Council that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was in the World, did not deem it in their Province to Judge or Cenſure the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Uſury in the Laity, but left that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Civil Magiſtrate, it is ſure a ſign of too great Boldneſs and Raſhneſs in any particular Clergy-man, upon leſs Authority to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49813:11"/>Cenſure and Damn all that deal in Uſury or Intereſt, as ſeveral have ignorantly or uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably done. And if there were a Law now in <hi>England</hi> forbidding the Clergy to take U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, how would this affect the Laity, or thoſe who follow Trades and Merchandiſe. We read, the Antichriſtian Apoſtacy had ſo prevailed in the Chriſtian Would, at the time even of this firſt General Council (which is ſaid to Conſiſt of Three hundred and eighteen Fathers) that even the generality of theſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were within an Ace of Eſtabliſhing that which the Apoſtle calls the Doctrine of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels, I mean <hi>Forbidding the Clergy to Marry;</hi> and the there was only one Biſhop that oppoſed the reſt, and turned the Scale on the right ſide: If they were ſo ready to bind all the Clergy to abſtain from Marriage, againſt the expreſs Doctrine and Determinations of the New Teſtament, no wonder if they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit the Clergy all Uſury, having a Colour or Pretence ſo to do from ſome old Teſtament Precepts, which do not oblige Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Now ſuppoſe, after this <hi>Nicene</hi> Council, a Man finds Uſury condemned in the Works or Writing of ſeveral Fathers or Doctors of the Church, ſo called; yet (I doubt not but)
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49813:11"/>a great many of them may be fairly interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to mean, either ſuch Uſury as was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden in the Law to be taken of the Poor, or ſuch as was forbidden by this <hi>Nicene</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil to be taken by the Clergy; neither of which will make at all againſt that Uſury I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend.</p>
            <p>If it be ſtill objected, That after this firſt Council there were afterwards other Councils and Doctors of the Church which did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn Uſury in all Caſes and Perſons. I grant it to be true; but then pray conſider their Grounds and Reaſons for it, and then you will not have a jot the worſe thought of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury upon the account of their Opinion. For from the time of this <hi>Nicene</hi> Council, the Church was continually growing more and more into that Antichriſtian Apoſtacy that did at laſt totally Eclipſe the Glory of it. And the Pope and Clergy by degrees began to encroach upon the Office and Laws of the Civil Magiſtrate, and ſo aſſumed to meddle and determine in Civil Matters, which did not belong to them. And ſince the Clergy were all forbidden to take Uſury by this firſt <hi>Nicene</hi> Council, many of them afterwards (partly through Envy, and partly through In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49813:12"/>as may rationally be ſuppos'd by their other Worldly and Ambitious Deſigns and Proceedings) made it their work to condemn all Uſury in the Laity; for had they been as much at liberty, as the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council left the Laity, I do not queſtion but the Clergy af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Council would have taken Uſury as much as the Clergy before the Council did, (which was the occaſion of that Councils De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree;) for we have no reaſon to believe, the Clergy that roſe up in ſucceſſive Ages after that Council, were better Men (or ſo good as) thoſe that lived at the time of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, or before it: Therefore ſeeing theſe Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy-men were totally forbid Uſury themſelves, they (not minding or regarding the vaſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between the Caſe of thoſe whoſe bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs it is to win Souls, and that of thoſe who are to drive Trades and follow Merchandize in the World) did afterwards condemn all Uſury in the Laity too; that by this means, as they could not lend to the Laity upon U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, they themſelves would not be bound to pay any uſury to the Laity, when they had occaſion to borrow of them: So that we have reaſon to believe it was Self-intereſt was the greateſt Cauſe of many of the Clergy's ſtick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling againſt uſury.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:49813:12"/>
            <p>Again, I would deſire any Man ſeriouſly to tell me, Whether the Cenſures or Opinions of any of the Fathers or Councils, after the firſt <hi>Nicene</hi> Council, are to be preferred to, or equalled with the Opinions or Cenſures of thoſe <hi>Nicene</hi> Fathers? If the Clergy at that time did exerciſe uſury (as the words of the Cannon do expreſly declare) no doubt but the Laity did practice it as much or more; and if it were ſo ſinful and damnable in its own Nature, as ſome have affirm'd it is, no doubt but thoſe Fathers (though they would not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to themſelves a Power to prohibit uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Laity, yet they) would at leaſt have earneſtly recommended it to the pious Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, that he would make a general Law to prohibit it in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his Dominions, which I cannot learn that ever he did, but only by his Edict con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed the Decree of this Council againſt the Clergies taking of uſury. But ſuppoſe the Emperour then, or any Civil Magiſtrate ſince, had by Civil Laws totally forbidden all uſury in their Dominions, both Clergy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Laity, unleſs it be in all caſes and curcumſtances a Moral Evil (which can never be proved) how are we in this Nation obliged by any ſuch
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49813:13"/>Laws? Are we of this Nation bound by the Laws of any other Country as ſuch, beſides and different from the Laws of our own?</p>
            <p>Again, Let us conſider, though many good Men in former times (whether before or ſince the Reformation) were indeed againſt all ſorts of Increaſe or Uſury upon lending Money, yet there are now, for ought I know, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny holy and good Men that hold it lawful: And why are we bound to the Judgment of the other more than of theſe. And by the way, this Conſideration, I humbly conceive, ſhou'd have moved Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> to have been leſs poſitive in declaring his Opinion upon this Point.</p>
            <p>His zealous, but raſh Cenſures of all Uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or Increaſe upon Loan of Money, has gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven (I doubt) a needleſs occaſion to many to have leſs regard (than otherwiſe they might have had) to his zealous Exhortations againſt thoſe other known Sins he juſtly condemns in his Sermon: I believe he would have done much better to have ſpoken againſt the Abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in Uſury, than the thing it ſelf. There are Sins enough (God knows) in the Nation, that are confeſſed by all to be ſuch, which will find Preachers work enough, ſo that they
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49813:13"/>will not need to be ſo peremptory againſt a thing which ſo many wiſe and good Men approve as lawful. That there are a great many abuſes in many caſes and circumſtances about lending Money upon uſe, I eaſily grant, (and am as heartily ſorry for, as they that are againſt Uſury) but the abuſe of a thing by ſome, yea by many, will not infer the unlawfulneſs of it: If ſo, then Buying, and Selling, and all ſorts of Tranding muſt be unlawful, becauſe abuſed by many, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed againſt the ſtrict Laws of Juſtice and Charity; yea, and the Office of preaching it ſelf, would then be unlawful, becauſe 'tis poſſible many (as I ſuppoſe Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> will not deny) may regard the Flock only, or chiefly for the Fleece ſake, or for filthy Lucre ſake.</p>
            <p>I ſhall in the next place conſider and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute ſome of the moſt material Arguments (that I have met with) whereby the Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of all Uſury would pretend to prove it unlawful in its own Nature, and to differ from other ways of diſpoſing Money upon Increaſe or Profit, (which all grant to be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful) and one is this; They ſay, If a Man lends Money, it's unreaſonable to take In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49813:14"/>beſides the Principal again; foraſmuch as Money naturally yields no Increaſe, but what is got by the pains of the Borrower, and not of the Lender: Whereas if a Man lets Land for profit, it naturally yields Fruit; and if one lets a Houſe, it will grow worſe by time and wearing, in conſideration whereof a Man receives Rent.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, and grant there is a difference between lending of Money and theſe other Inſtances, in ſome circumſtances; but for the moſt part, little or nothing in the ſubſtance: For though Land naturally yields Increaſe, yet it will not do ſo proportionably to the full Rent required, without the great Pains and Labour of the Tenant; (in which the Landlord does not concern himſelf, any more than a Man that lends Money does in the Improvement of it) And if Tenants by Leaſe are bound to Repair Houſes (and to leave them repaired at the End of the Term) beſides paying their Rents, then there is very little difference in the reaſon of the Caſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween letting for Rent, and letting at Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt; and eſpecially where a Man lets a piece of Ground to build on, reſerving a certain Ground-Rent during the Leaſe; for this
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49813:14"/>Ground (it may be) is not worth five ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings a year unbuilt, (for what will grow upon it naturally) when yet a Ground-Rent of five pounds a year may be made of it; and nevertheleſs all the Improvement is pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at the charge, and by the Pains and Induſtry of the Tenant, and nothing by the Owner of the Ground; and when he has built his Houſe, though he cannot get a Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant for it a great while, or though he looſes Rent by bad Tenants; yet the Ground Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord expects his Ground-Rent, and thinks he may do it honeſtly and lawfully. And when the Term of the Leaſe iſ expired, this Ground (that naturally of it ſelf could have yielded ſo very little in compariſon, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hout the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants Charge and Pains) is left up to the Landlord in as good a plight as any Money upon Uſury when it is repaid, beſides all the Buildings upon it, which may be worth much more than the Ground it ſelf: And I ſuppoſe no Pleader againſt Uſury would think it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful to be ſuch a Landlord. There iſ but one Circumſtance wherein this Inſtance differs conſiderably in reference to the matter in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, from that of lending Money on Uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and that it, Principal Money in the Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowers
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49813:15"/>hand is liable to Providential loſs in Trading, or otherwiſe, but Ground is not; which I grant to be true: But a Houſe built on Ground is liable to be burnt or demoliſhed, and a Tenant in that Caſe is bound to build it again, and yet the Ground Landlord will look for all his Rent; and the ſame is agreed and expected where a Houſe is let by Leaſe upon a Rack-Rent.</p>
            <p>Another great Argument why Uſury is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, ſay ſome, is this, It is hurtful not only to the Borrower, but to the Commonwealth in general: For when People borrow upon Uſury to carry on their Trades, they will ſet their Goods at higher Prices, to enable them to pay Uſe-money, which otherwiſe they could af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford cheaper.</p>
            <p>But if this Argument be an Argument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Uſury, it will much more be ſo alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Houſe-rents, for were it not for Rents, all Trades-men might afford their Goods Cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; and ſome have as much need to hire Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, as Houſes, to carry on their Trades. But I conceive this Argument is more in conceit than in reality. 'Tis true, if all Trades-men of one and the ſame Trade did borrow Money upon Intereſt, it might occaſion ſome Increaſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49813:15"/>of Prices; but if only ſome do, it is plain they muſt ſell as cheap as the reſt that do not bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Money are willing to do, unleſs they will loſe their Cuſtomers. To me it is very plain, That were there a Law made and truly obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that no Money ſhould be lent at Intereſt, (unleſs at the ſame time a Law could be made that men who have ſpare Money ſhould be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to lend without Uſury, which is never like to be) this would be far more prejudicial to the Commonwealth, and more occaſion the dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Prices than the Law to lend upon Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt would; for in caſe of a general Reſtraint of taking Intereſt, I think it is very plain, few would lend Money, becauſe they would not only be ſure of receiving no profit by it, but muſt run the riſque of loſing it for nothing: Now in this caſe, only the great and rich men and Traders, that have Money enough of their own, would engroſs the moſt uſeful Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to themſelves, and make their own Prices; and inferiour Traders for want of Moneys to buy at the ſame Market, muſt be forced to buy of them at their price, which might make Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities as dear again to common Buyers, as they would have been, in caſe a general biberty of lending upon moderate Increaſe were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49813:16"/>when by paying 5 or 6 <hi>per Cent.</hi> they may get or ſave 10 or 20 <hi>per Cent.</hi> or more. And therefore I am fully perſwaded, were a Law againſt all Uſury put in Execution, the prices of all ſorts of Goods would immediately riſe very conſiderably. And then what muſt thoſe many Widows and Orphans, and ſeveral others do, that have nothing but Money to live on, and are not in a capacity to manage Trades, they muſt not lend it for profit, they cannot trade with it; why the next thing they muſt pitch upon is, to buy Houſes or Land with it; this will im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately raiſe Houſes and Lands to exceſſive prices as to Purchaſe, and by conſequence to ſuch low Rents as will not anſwer the value of the Money, nor give perhaps ſo much as 2 or 3 <hi>per Cent.</hi> improvement: Whether this would be an Advantage to the Publick, I leave to the conſidering Reader to judge.</p>
            <p>And if thoſe who are againſt all Uſury, would have Chriſtians perpetually obliged to particular Precepts that were given to the Jews in their Laws, ſhould they not be much more poſitive from Goſpel Precepts to maintain it unlawful for Chriſtians to ſwear in any caſe, or to eat Pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings made with blood, or any thing that dyes by ſtrangling, than out of the Jewiſh Law to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49813:16"/>maintain it unlawful for Chriſtians to lend Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for Increaſe.</p>
            <p>The ſum of all is, If moderate Uſury or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe (rightly circumſtantiated) be not in its own nature unlawful, as againſt Juſtice, though to require it in ſome caſes may be againſt Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and if thoſe Precepts the Jews were under, in this Particular, do not perpetually oblige Chriſtians, any more than thoſe other Inſtances of Charity to which they were obliged, then I conclude, It is the Law of every Chriſtian Country, and the Judgment of a Conſcientious Man, that muſt ſtate this Matter, what degrees of Intereſt upon Lending ſhall be lawful or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, both in general and in particular Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances; and this Law, we of this Country muſt have recourſe to in this Matter; and (as in Civil Matters the Goſpel commands us to be <hi>Subject to every Ordinance of Man for the Lord's ſake,</hi> ſo) we muſt herein be ſubject to that which the Wiſdom of the Nation (in the Legiſlative Power thereof) has determined. And by this Law a Chriſtian is left at Liberty to lend, either in a way of common Juſtice for Increaſe, or of Kindneſs or Charity freely, as the Nature and Circumſtances of the Caſe may require.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> I know ſome object again, The Law
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49813:17"/>of the Land doth not allow Uſury, only for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids taking more than ſo much in the Hundred; therefore there is no pleading the lawfulneſs of Uſury from the Law. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Which I take to be a very weak Argument, and that it has little force in it; the Judges in Law and Equity (I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) are beſt able to determine what the Law allows as to this Matter, when ſo many Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are given every Term, as well in Equity as in Law, That the Plaintiffs ſhall not only have their Money, but Intereſt alſo; which if the Law did not allow and approve as juſt, the Judges would not thus determine. Put caſe there were a Law that no Landlord ſhould take above ſo much Rent for Houſes in ſuch a place, or of ſuch or ſuch Dimenſions, would it hence follow, the Law doth not allow or approve of taking any Rent at all? I doubt this would be but a weak Inference, and the other is no better.</p>
            <p>Now ſuppoſing the taking of Increaſe for lending Money be lawful in its own Nature to Chriſtians, (which I hope has been ſufficiently proved) the next thing to be conſidered is, Whether it be convenient, that is, whether the allowance of a moderate Increaſe be good for the Nation in general, or not; or whether it
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49813:17"/>would be better for the Nation that no ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe were allowed to be given or taken. I have hinted ſomething already of the Benefit to the Commonwealth that comes by allowance of Intereſt, in making Goods cheaper. I ſhall now in a few Particulars ſhew ſome further Advantages thereof to the Kingdom, which are never like to be obtained by a Prohibition of all Intereſt: As,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Were it not for the Allowance of a moderate Increaſe for lending Money, thouſands that want would never be accommodated, which now are.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Though moſt that lend ſhould do it freely, yet they that borrow of them would in this way be liable to ſeveral Inconveniencies which may be as prejudicial to them, if not more than paying Intereſt; as thus, Suppoſe a Man wants a Sum of Money, his Friend tells him he will lend him freely for ſuch a time perhaps 3 or 6 Months, but if he does not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pay it again by that time, he ſhall be much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured for the want of it; the Borrower promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to repay it accordingly; but ſo it happens, when the time comes, he cannot do it: This occaſions a Quarrel, it may be a Suit between the Lender and him; the Lender ſaith he is
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49813:18"/>damnified, and ought to have Damage-money given him (for I find ſome Anti-uſurers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves do allow that Damage-money ought to be given the Lender in ſuch Caſes) Now who ſhall be Judge of the Quantity of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage-money, and whether the Damage-money (and Charges about it) in many Caſes, if not in moſt, may not exceed a moderate Intereſt for the Money during the whole time it was lent: Eſpecially conſidering that the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie in adjuſting the Proportion of Damage-money, may alſo it ſelf occaſion a Law-ſuit, though the Principal ſhould not.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, This is another Inconveniency, People that lend freely for the moſt part will not lend their Money for ſo long a time as the generality of Borrowers need it; and the Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in of Money exactly at the times of Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, may prove to their greater prejudice in ſome Circumſtances, than paying Intereſt for all the time: But now when Money is lent upon moderate Increaſe, the Intereſt-Money goes on though the Day of Payment be paſt; this is a great Motive to the Lender to continue the Money as the Borrowers Occaſions require.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, By borrowing freely, I lay a need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Obligation upon my ſelf to lend as much
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49813:18"/>Money to the Lender, or to be Surety for him another time; either of which (in ſome Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances which he or I may be then in) may be very enſnaring and dangerous to me. Again, how many Children are ſent up out of the Countries every day to be Apprentices in Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Towns; and the Parents and Friends of moſt of them it may be with difficulty find Money to put them out to Apprentice, but can give them no Stock to ſet up their Trades; yet many of theſe having been obſerved to be dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and careful during their Apprenticeſhip, have been Encouraged to ſet up when out of their Times, and Monies offered them (upon paying moderate Intereſt) to enable them ſo to do; and this has been the raiſing of many Perſons, I may ſay multitudes, which otherwiſe muſt have lived Journey-men or Servants. Again, How many Gentlemen are there, who have Eſtates in Land, and but little Money, that have Daughters to diſpoſe in Marriage, whoſe Advancements are ſucceſsfully promoted by borrowing Money at Intereſt upon their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Eſtates, which otherwiſe could not be effected. Again, what more promotes the Trade and Merchandize of the Nation than the frequent Lending and Borrowing of Money;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49813:19"/>for Money is as requiſite to be paſs'd too and fro for the maintaining of Trade, as the Circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Blood and Spirits is for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of Health in the Body, as all that have Judgment and Experience in thoſe Affairs know very well. Now what either equal or probable way is there to furniſh ſuch Sums as the Caſes of greater Dealers require, without paying Intereſt for it. And therefore, by the way, I ſee not but that the Trade or Employment of Banking it ſelf is very Convenient, if not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the preſent accommodation of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants and other conſiderable Traders upon ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Important Occaſions: And therefore, I think, that upbraiding Reflexion which Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> has quoted from Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> namely, <hi>That a Man ſhould be born for nothing elſe but to tell out Money, and to take in Paper,</hi> is but weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grounded, for thoſe are but the Inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal and Subſervient part of their main Buſineſs, which is or may be the convenient helping and ſupplying of other Men's Affairs, and getting reaſonable Advantage to themſelves. And if this be a neceſſary and uſeful Calling to a Trading Nation, why is it not as lawful to be telling Money for that purpoſe, as to be buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſelling, and turning over Goods for as long a time.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:49813:19"/>
            <p>It is true, Chriſt drave the Exchangers out of the Temple, ſo he did the Sellers of Doves; but he condemned neither of the Callings as unlawful in themſelves, but becauſe of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitableneſs of the Place: For it ſeems there were Bankers of Exchangers in Chriſt's Time, which he himſelf alludes to, when he Cenſures the ſlothful Servant for not putting his Talent to ſuch, that ſo Chriſt might have had his own again with Uſury: What need I ſay more, It is Increaſe for Money that Encourages to lend for Supplying the preſent Neceſſities of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and will the better enable to furniſh Moneys for the further Supplies of it when they ſhall be call'd for.</p>
            <p>Now let any man prove, if he can, that ſo many good Effects would proceed from a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Prohibition of all Increaſe for Lending, and whether any ſuppoſe Prejudice or Miſchief that may come to a Borrower by paying Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, can or ought to be an Argument never to lend at Intereſt, I am very well ſatisfied there are few Inſtances to be produced of any that have been ruined by borrowing at Intereſt, but who would have been ruined alſo had they borrowed without Intereſt, and that there are more Inſtances of ſuch who have been ruined
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49813:20"/>by buying of Goods, or paying Rents for Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes or Lands.</p>
            <p>I would here alſo ſhew that Lending Money at ſuch Intereſt as our Laws allow, is liable to fewer Deceits or Frauds than ſelling moſt ſorts of Goods: As ſuppoſe one ſells 20 <hi>l.</hi> worth of Goods for ready Money, the Buyer may be deceived (and often is) as to the goodneſs of the Commodity, and for the moſt part he is Ignorant of the Sellers profit, neither of which Lending at Increaſe is liable to. Again, If the Buyer keeps his Goods a while by him, the Market may fall (which frequently happens) and then the Goods which coſt 20 <hi>l.</hi> may not be worth 15 <hi>l.</hi> but the keeping Money by me never ſo long does not diminiſh the value. Again, In ſelling Goods a man may return his Money ſo many times a year, as to get 20, 30, 40, 50, <hi>per Cent. per Annum,</hi> or more; whereas in lending Money I am limitted to that mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Increaſe <hi>per Annum</hi> which the Law al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows; nor can I take or exact any more with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out endangering the loſs or forfeiture of my Principal Money: So that on the Lender's part, though he were a Knave, there can be no deceit at all (which is the commoneſt Abuſe in Dealing) impos'd upon the Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49813:20"/>by Lending to him at Intereſt.</p>
            <p>I hope the World will not interpret my Attempt in this Nature, as if I deſign'd or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended only to ſhew my ſelf an Enemy to Mr. <hi>Jones;</hi> I am ſo far from that, That I bleſs God for him, and for his Diligence and Faithfulneſs in preaching againſt the Corruptions of the Times: Nor do I think much the worſe of him, for his Miſtake or Error in this matter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Uſury, (ſuppoſing it not a wilful one) only I think he ſhould have taken more time and conſideration about a Point of ſo great weight and concernment to many thouſands, and well weighed the Arguments of thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny living Saints that are for it, as well as thoſe dead ones that have been againſt it: Nor would I be deemed an Enemy to any truly holy Men or Fathers, that in former Ages have been of his Judgment; whoſe great Love to Charity and good Works, (together with their Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Nature of Traffick and Commerce, not conſidering that more Monies are needed for the carrying of it on, that can be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by free Loan) in a Concern of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture might eaſily incline their Judgments to determine in favour of that Opinion, which they thought would moſt advance Well-doing,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49813:21"/>namely, That the Lending of Money ſhould be always in a way of Charity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and never in a way of Common Juſtice; which I doubt not (by what has been ſaid) will appear to be a Miſtake, though it may be called a right hand Error.</p>
            <p>But if any Perſon yet remains unſatisfied with what I have proved and alledg'd in Vindication of this Subject of Intereſt, and thinks fit to make a Reply thereto, I deſire he would di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly make out and prove, if he can, what unavoidable Moral Evil or Damage redounds to any Perſon, or to the Publick, by Giving and Taking Intereſt for Money; and from which the Practice of it cannot be freed or ſeparated by any Circumſtances.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THe Ingenious and Diverting Letters of the Lady — Travels into <hi>Spain.</hi> Deſcribing the Devotions, Nunneries, Humours, Cuſtoms, Laws, Militia, Trade, Diet, and Recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of that People. Intermixt with great variety of Modern Adventures, and ſurpriſing Accidents: being the trueſt and beſt Remarks extant on that Court and Country. In 3 Parts compleat. Printed for <hi>S. Crouch</hi> at the Corner of <hi>Pope</hi>'s-<hi>Head-Alley, Cornhill.</hi> 1692.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49813:21"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
